Teacher Education Development Service; Records ua658
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Teacher Education Development Service Records
1971-1977
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
State University of New York at Albany. Teacher Education Development Service
ua658
4 cubic ft.
A joint federal and state grant-funded program to implement competency-based teacher education (CBTE) and develop a statewide collaborative system of support for additional CBTE efforts.
4 audiotapes and 4 filmstrips
Administrative History
From the mid-twentieth century, there were numerous attempts in several colleges and universities in the United States in the area of teacher education reform. Many experimental projects were launched in order to identify the least effective aspect of teacher training so as to change it while leaving all the other traditional parts intact. It was in this context that competency-based teacher education (CBTE) was developed along with the concomitant field-centeredness, cooperative decision making and constituency parity pointing the way to a method of teacher training that rests solely upon experience and knowledge while it moves to a radical concept and style. In an effort to meet the challenge of improving teacher preparation programs, the State University of New York at Albany proposed that a Center be founded in 1973. This Center would develop and make operational a competency-based teacher education program with the State University of New York at Albany. A Teacher Corps internship program in Schenectady, New York would further develop and modify the professional education and internship portions of the program. This Center would also help the New York State Department of Education to make thirteen trial projects fully operational schemes by providing materials, mediation, and consultants. The Center would also help in non-trial project teacher-training institutions to meet the New York State CBTE mandate by providing training, consultants, and materials for program development. The Center would also develop a statewide collaborative system of support for the development and functioning of teacher education in the CBTE mode.
It was in this context that the Teacher Education Development Service was founded in 1973 and funded under grant No. 300760034 jointly supported by the United States Office of Education, the State University of New York at Albany, and the New York State Department of Education. All policy decisions were made by a group which included a Bureau Chief of the New York State Department of Education who was officially designated to this post by the Division Director. The Teacher Education Development Service, or TEDS, presented conferences and workshops across the state, helping teacher-trainers to improve their programs. A number of object-specific training modes were developed and used during these activities. TEDS also developed a research library that provided materials and services to more than ninety individuals who represented institutions and programs. The meetings of representatives from the New York State Teacher Corps Network laid the groundwork for a statewide communications system in support of CBTE. The staff of TEDS participated in producing and presenting materials to aid both trial-project and non-trial-project sites develop a CBTE program. During 1975-1976, work continued to strengthen the ability of TEDS to service the institutions of New York State. In order to assess effectiveness and project need, both in-state and out-of-state, a research project was commenced entitled Factors Affecting Institutional Development of CBTE programs. A research team, composed of twelve professors from four departments in the School of Education at the State University of New York at Albany, designed and implemented a study sampling thirty-two colleges and forty programs of teacher preparation in New York State. The results of this research yielded data pertinent to the implementation of CBTE and the process of institutional program change. Two additional projects were subsequently added: one concerned the identification of characteristics of individuals who were applying for teacher certification in New York State. This study was undertaken to determine if new policies on teacher certification needed to be developed and new facilities constructed so as to keep pace with the evolution of teacher training and certification at large. The second project investigated the elements of program design within institutions in New York State and how these were perceived by staff that conducted program review at the Division of Teacher Education and Certification.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the organization, evolution, scope, thinking, research, activities, and programs of the Teacher Education Development Service. Of particular interest in this collection are four audiotapes and four filmstrips, which provide an audiovisual overview of CBTE.
Topics which are extensively documented in this collection include: the certification program of speech, language and hearing specialists; conferences; Community Legal Education Project; course materials; dissertation abstracts; the Mutual Involvement Review Activity; Skidmore College Proposal; Teacher Education Certification Consortium; team leader evaluation of interns; Teacher Corps Programs; and the Youth Tutoring Youth program.
Several collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives provide further information on education and policy issues that were of concern to the faculty, staff, and students of the Teacher Education Development Service. Of particular note are the records of the Capital Area School Development Association (APAP065), the School of Education (UA650), and the Center for Community Studies (UA652.004).
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is divided into three series: Administrative File, Activities and Programs, and Publications - each ordered alphabetically.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives. 1988 June
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Schenectady, New York; Education; Teacher education; UAlbany Centers & Institutes; State University of New York at Albany; State University of New York at Albany. Department of Teacher Education
- Administrative Files, 1971-1977; 1; 0.75 cubic ft.; 4 audiotapes, 4 filmstrips
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of materials relating directly to the operations of the Teacher Education and Development Center and to some of its faculty and staff. The series includes agendae, bibliographies, brochures, the Community Board meeting minutes, Elementary Teacher Education Program descriptions, reports, memoranda, minutes, material related to the research library and resource center, and the Teacher Corps SUNYA-Schenectady Project material. The series also includes four audiotapes and four filmstrips, which provide an audiovisual overview of CBTE.
  - Agendae, 1973 November 29 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Bibliographies, 1974-1977 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Bibliographies, 1974-1977 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Brochures, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Committee on Doctoral Programs, 1975 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - The Community Board - Meeting Minutes, 1973 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Elementary Teacher Education Program Descriptions, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Health Insurance, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - Interim Report, 1974 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Interim Report, 1974 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Intern Review Form, 1973 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Memoranda, 1971-1973 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 1973 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
  - Modules List, 1974 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 14)
  - Program Descriptions, 1976 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 15)
  - Research Library, 1976 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 16)
  - Resource Center, 1974 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 17)
  - Semi-annual Report, 1975-1976 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 18)
  - Teacher Corps SUNYA-Schenectady Project - Minutes, 1971-1973 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 19)
  - "Introduction to CBTE: Part 1 Overview," Audiotape and Filmstrip, Undated (Reel 1)
  - "Introduction to CBTE: Part 2 Governance," Audiotape and Filmstrip, Undated (Reel 2)
  - "Introduction to CBTE: Part 3 Curriculum Model," Audiotape and Filmstrip, Undated (Reel 3)
  - "Introduction to CBTE: Part 4 Program Development," Audiotape and Filmstrip, Undated (Reel 4)
- Activities and Programs, 1971-1977; 2; 1 cubic ft.
  This series contains materials relating directly to the activities and programs of the Teacher Education Development Service. Topics of interest include certification program of speech, language, and hearing specialists; conferences; the Community Legal Education Project; course materials; dissertation abstracts; Mutual Involvement Review Activity; Skidmore College Proposal; Teacher Education Certification Consortium; team leader evaluation of interns; Teacher Corps Programs; and the Youth Tutoring Youth program.
  - Adolescent Psychology Course, 1972-1973 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 20)
  - Andrews, Theodore E., Its Wisdom and Folly, Paper, 1972 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 21)
  - Assessing the Unaffiliated, Report, 1976 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 22)
  - Baum, Richard J., Evaluative Summary and Chronology of the SUNYA- Schenectady Teacher Corps Project, 1971-1973 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 23)
  - Central Dark School Teacher Corps Program, 1971 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 24)
  - Certification of Speech, Language and Hearing Specialists, Undated (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 25)
  - Community/Association Course, Undated (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 26)
  - Competence-Based Teacher Education, 1972-1974 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 27)
  - Competence-Based Teacher Education in Transition Conference, 1977 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 28)
  - Competency-Based Teacher Education Modules, Undated (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 29)
  - Conference of New Starts, 1975 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 30)
  - Darcy, C. Michael, Matrix for CBTE Design, 1944 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 31)
  - Eighth Cycle Role Group Conference, 1973 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 32)
  - Eighth Cycle Teacher Corps Conference, 1973 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 33)
  - Farmer, Walter A., and Farrell, Margaret A., Albany Mathematics and Science Teaching Program, Undated (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 34)
  - Farmer, Walter A., Farrell, Margaret A., Clark, Richard M., Test Competency as Related to Classroom Performance, Albany, NY, 1977 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 35)
  - Farrell, Margaret A., Farmer, Walter A., Clark, Richard, Field Testing: A Systems Analysis Model for Mathematics/ Science Teacher Education, Paper, 1976 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 36)
  - Darcy, C. Michael, Working through a Consortium, Paper, 1974 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 37)
  - Ganeles, Dan, Competence-Based Teacher Education as Viewed by the Teacher Education Development Service, 1974 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 38)
  - Ganeles, Dan, Competence-Based Instruction, Book 1: A Model Curriculum Structure for a CBI Program an Explanation and Description, 1975 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 39)
  - Ganeles, Dan, Competence-Based Instruction, Book 2: Task Book, 1976 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 40)
  - Ganeles, Dan, A Hierarchy of Experience, Papers, 1975 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 41)
  - Ganeles, Dan, A Rationale for Competence-Based Teacher Education: A Humanistic Approach, 1974 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 42)
  - Ganeles, Dan, A Rationale for Competence-Based Instruction, Paper, 1976 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 43)
  - Ganeles, Dan, The Experiential "Domain", Paper, 1975 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 44)
  - Glowacki, Sue, and Joe Parisi, "Mont Pleasant Team Teaching", 1973 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 45)
  - In-service Course, 1973-1975 (Box 1 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 46)
  - Lewis, Richard W., Jr., and Robert J. Neiderberger, An Analysis and Critique of the SUNYA Competency-Based Program in Educational Administration, Paper, 1976 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 1)
  - Mount Pleasant High School Teacher Corps Program, 1971 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 2)
  - Mutual Involvement Review Activity, 1973-1974 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 3)
  - A New Style of Certification, 1971 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 4)
  - Notes, Undated (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 5)
  - OBrien, Robert, Volunteer Teacher Corps Project Proposal, Home Maintenance and Improvement Project, 1972 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 6)
  - Oneida Teacher Corps Program, 1971 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 7)
  - Oneida Team Training Workshop, 1972-1973 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 8)
  - Quirk, Thomas J., Teacher Accountability: Pitfalls and Promise, Address, 1972 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 9)
  - Roth, Roberta, Teacher Competencies and Assessment Techniques, Washington D.C., 1975 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 10)
  - Skidmore Proposal, 1973 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 11)
  - Snyder, Gerald and Dan Ganeles, Secondary Social Studies Course, 1972 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 12)
  - Socio-Cultural Foundations Course, 1973 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 13)
  - Socio-Cultural Foundations Course, Undated (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 14)
  - Stack, Ray, Man: A Course of Study, 1973 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 15)
  - Steinmetz Junior High School Teacher Corps Program, 1971-1973 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 16)
  - Teacher Corps, 1971-1973 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 17)
  - Teacher Education Certification Consortium SUNYA, 1974 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 18)
  - Teaching of Reading Course, Undated (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 19)
  - Teaching of Reading Course, Undated (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 20)
  - Teaching Theories and Practices, 1973 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 21)
  - Teaching Theories and Practices, Part 3, Teaching Strategies Course, Undated (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 22)
  - Team Leader Evaluation of Interns, Teacher Corps Project, 1972 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 23)
  - Team Leader Evaluation of Interns, Teacher Corps Project, 1972 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 24)
  - Team Leader Evaluation of Interns, Teacher Corps Project, 1972 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 25)
  - Value Clarification Course, 1974 Summer (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 26)
  - Youth Tutoring Youth, 1971-1972 (Box 2 (2-Activities and Programs), Folder 27)
- Publications, 1971-1977; 3; 2.25 cubic ft.
  This series includes project reports, published papers by staff, proposals, published programs and course materials, and workshop programs.
  - Baldwin, Alexinia Y., and Dennis J. Nielson, Technical Assistance, 1976 (Box 2 (3-Publications), Folder 28)
  - Baum, Richard D., Evaluative Summary and Chronology of the SUNYA-Schenectady Teacher Corps Project, 1971-1973 (Box 2 (3-Publications), Folder 29)
  - Benedict, Marjorie A., Catalog of Holdings Teacher Education Developmental Service, 1975 (Box 2 (3-Publications), Folder 30)
  - Bosco, Joseph A., Team Teaching, Undated (Box 2 (3-Publications), Folder 31)
  - Campbell, Robert, Fred Como, Beverly Elander, Janet Johnson, Gene Marrow, Team Leader Evaluation of Interns, Second Edition, 1974 Fall (Box 2 (3-Publications), Folder 32)
  - Como, Fredrick N., Course, Socio-Cultural Foundations, 1976 (Box 2 (3-Publications), Folder 33)
  - Competency-Based Teacher Education, Glossary of Terms, 1974 (Box 2 (3-Publications), Folder 34)
  - Competency-Based Teacher Education, Conference, 1973 (Box 2 (3-Publications), Folder 35)
  - Competency-Based Teacher Education, Conference, 1974 (Box 2 (3-Publications), Folder 36)
  - Competence-Based Teacher Education in Transition Conference, 1977 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 1)
  - Competence-Based Teacher Education Program, Mathematics, 1976 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 2)
  - Competence-Based Teacher Education Program, Natural Science, 1976 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 3)
  - Competence-Based Teacher Education, Second Interim Report, Undated (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 4)
  - Darcy, C. Michael, The Delphi Technique Aid to Policy Formation, 1977 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 5)
  - Darcy, C. Michael, Education, Class, the US and the UK: Implications for Teacher Training, Paper, 1976 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 6)
  - Darcy, C. Michael, The Induction Scheme as Viewed by Certain Primary Head Teachers, Paper, 1976 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 7)
  - Darcy, C. Michael, A Simulation Report, 1975 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 8)
  - Darcy, C. Michael, John A. Ether, Judith Adrezin, Daniel Ganales, Mira for CBTE, 1974 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 9)
  - Darcy, C. Michael, Dan Ganeles, John A. Ether, A CBTE Curriculum Model and Directions, 1975 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 10)
  - Cooke, Kathleen G. and Jennifer Whittle, Factors Affecting the Institutional Development of CBTE Programs, Vol. 1, 1976 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 11)
  - Bystydzienski, Jill M., Charles R. Hancock, Joseph A. Scimecca, Jennifer Whittle, Factors Affecting the Institutional Development of CBTE Programs, vol. 2, 1976 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 12)
  - Deluca, Nicholas M., Factors Affecting the Institutional Development of CBTE Programs, vol. 4, 1976 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 13)
  - Edelfelt, Roy A., Ronald Corwin, Elizabeth Hanna, Lessons from the Teacher Corps, Washington, D.C., 1974 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 14)
  - Eighth Cycle Teacher Corps, Proposal, 1972 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 15)
  - Fox, G. Thomas, Jr., Federal Role in School Reform from Sociological and Educational Perspectives, 1974 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 16)
  - Howes, Nancy J., Factors Affecting the Institutional Development of CBTE Programs, 1976 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 17)
  - Howes, Nancy J., Leadership Process, 1976 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 18)
  - Interim Evaluation Report on the Twelfth Cycle Teacher Corps Project, 1978 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 19)
  - Lis, Donna, Educational Psychology Course, 1975 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 20)
  - Module Workshop, Undated (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 21)
  - NCRIEEO Tip Sheet No. 10, 1973 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 22)
  - Performance-Based Teacher Education newsletter (PBTE), 1973 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 23)
  - Portal Schools Monthly Newsletter, 1973 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 24)
  - Problems of Competency-Based Teacher Education, Second Interim Report, 1972 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 25)
  - Problems of Competency-Based Teacher Education, 1974 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 26)
  - Report of Activities, 1975 March-April (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 27)
  - Research Library Catalog of Holdings, 1975 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 28)
  - Research Library Catalog of Holdings, 1975 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 29)
  - Research Library Catalog of Holdings, 1975 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 30)
  - Rostetter, David J., Factors Affecting CBTE Program Development: From the Perspective of Inter and Intre-Organizational Conflict, 1976 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 31)
  - Rostetter, David J., Factor Affecting CBTE Program Development as Reported by Institutions and the New York State Education Department, 1976 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 32)
  - Second Quarterly Report SUNYA-Schenectady School District Teacher Corps, 1976-1977 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 33)
  - Sixth Cycle Teacher Corps Program, 1970-1972 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 34)
  - Sixth Cycle Teacher Corps Program, 1971 (Box 3 (3-Publications), Folder 35)
  - Teacher Corps Final Report, 1971-1973 (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 1)
  - Teacher Corps Information Booklet, 1973 (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 2)
  - Teacher Education Certification Consortium, 1977 (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 3)
  - Teaching English as a Second Language, 1979 (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 4)
  - Teaching of Reading Course, Undated (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 5)
  - Teaching of Reading Cluster 1, 1974-1975 (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 6)
  - Teaching of Reading Cluster 3, 1974-1975 (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 7)
  - Teaching of Reading Cluster 4, 1974-1975 (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 8)
  - Teaching Theories and Practice Course, Undated (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 9)
  - Teaching Theories and Practices Eighth Cycle Teacher Corps Program, 1973-1974 (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 10)
  - Tenth Cycle Teacher Corps Proposal, 1975 (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 11)
  - Tenth Cycle Teacher Corps Proposal, 1975 (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 12)
  - Tolbert, Ira, Telephone Survey of State Educational Department Activity Regarding Assessment Centers and /or Assessment Processes, 1976 (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 13)
  - Tolbert, Ira, and Elizabeth H. Clark, Appendix to a Descriptive Profile of Individuals Applying for Certification through Individual Review Procedures, 1976 (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 14)
  - Tolbert, Ira, and Elizabeth H. Clark, A Descriptive Profile of Individuals Applying for Certification through Individual Review Procedures, 1976 (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 15)
  - Tolbert, Ira, and Elizabeth H. Clark, A Descriptive Profile of Individuals Applying for Certification through Individual Review Procedures, 1976 (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 16)
  - Twelfth Cycle Teacher Corps Proposal, 1976 (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 17)
  - SUNYA-Schenectady Teacher Corps Project, Eighth Cycle Teacher Corps Proposal, 1973 (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 18)
  - SUNYA-Schenectady Teacher Corps Project, Eighth Cycle Teacher Corps Proposal, 1973 (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 19)
  - Town Meeting: Housing an Interaction Exercise Workshop, 1973 (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 20)
  - Workshop Program, Undated (Box 4 (3-Publications), Folder 21)